Bunty I must confess I tend to be rather
relaxed when it comes to deep
contemplation and reflection on life's
intricacies however I take solace in the fact that
however I take solace in the fact that
my idleness doesn't lead me astray
I stand firmly in my virtuous path
so can I simply find contentment in this
virtue rest in my accomplishments and
trust that wisdom will come naturally
with time
well it's a bit of a broad of a question
there because there's so many other
factors within that
dances both yes or no
you could if you remain virtuous
protecting that virtue protecting them
the wholesome action avoiding the
unwholesome action even if you don't
necessarily are kind of exerting
yourself in some
effort to understand higher Dharma or or
more specific aspects of it
you you you could be progressing if on
the other hand like you you're virtuous
you're not breaking the precepts but at
the same time you're not watching
intentions in subtler actions within
that then not necessarily you might you might
then not necessarily you might you might
not be uh regressing
as much but at the same time you're not
abandoning the assumptions that you
carry the value of sensuality that you
carry the wrong views that you carry
so there is no status quo basically
right in developing forward in terms of
the right practice or you are going
backward in terms of accumulating the
wrong views
because what you may what what this
person might think is virtuous well
exactly that's what it means like so you
might you might be slowing down your
accumulation of wrong views
through being virtuous and sensory
straining careful
but you need to undo them because you
have not started in a neutral position
you started by carrying all this burden
of ignore and savija and everything else
upon it and that needs to be undone
so what they are really asking is would
that be undone if I just remain virtuous
it could be it would take a lot longer
so you might run out of time basically
it might not be in this lifetime
[Music] it would take a lot longer and then also
it would take a lot longer and then also
again it's not just about oh I'm just
keeping the precepts religiously
superstitiously but well does that imply you're uh
but well does that imply you're uh
you're also Discerning your mind rooted
in unwholesome intentions
is that becoming obvious because many
people can many people do keep precepts
religious superstitiously in the sense
of I will abstain from doing this doing
these things and that's how Devas and
gods will protect me
so that's my that's the extent of my
effort I just not do this not because I
know and see for myself that it's bad to
do it it's just because I've been told
to and I have I have that kind of uh
belief that that will save me or it will
eventually to my Liberation it's like
well in and of itself that's just a nice
virtuous behavior that can as the Buddha
as the suit is described maybe lead you
to a heaven or something
if you if you kind of adhere to it in
this lifetime but that will run out
eventually so Faith doesn't necessarily
develop wisdom no no of course no so so
it's like you can you can just focus on
the virtual find contentment in it but
at the same time okay so now on top of
it
yep I will not make any detailed effort
and like really exerting myself in in
anxious Pursuits of understanding the
Dharma but when unwholesome things arise
in my mind although they are not against
the precepts you know by Body am I
entertaining them mentally am I seeing
the danger there do I see where my
intentions are rooted am I avoiding it
am I cultivating it am I enduring it if
the answer to those things are no then
your virtue is kind of well sterilized
he's just gonna stay there and you have
some benefits and that's it
it's still nicer than not being virtuous
but that's not what we're talking about
we're talking about whether that can
translate into into development in terms
of the Dharma and purified or completely
accomplishing virtue would be being an
arhand so are you completely
well yeah I mean accomplished in virtue
can mean being a sodapana
um and then fully purifying that can
lead to other hand ships so exactly like
what you are
finding contentment in
is it the virtue of a sotopana already
or it's cleared unsure in which case
like they will be a bit too risky to
find contentment in that if only if to
find condemn it only in that
because if you're still a putugina
you're not accomplished in virtue
although you might not be breaking the
precepts you have not seen it for
yourself good is good bad is bad
skillful is skillful unskillful is
unskillful you have not understood the root of
you have not understood the root of
suffering in the way out so you don't
see where the virtue is correctly
and that needs to be seen then if you
want to remain contented with that and
not maybe make further effort
Joe but even then it's like by that
point it would not be such a
tremendous task because now you know
what you need to do so you would just
basically be able to do it through your
virtue uh practicing withdrawal from
unwholesome States guarding of the sense
those would be would be enough actually
you would be progressing wisdom if you
have the right View
and another thing that comes to mind is
it's nice
to
rest in your virtue like two
you know to experience the joy of being
virtuous of being blameless that's very
nice that in a way it's uh
that in a way it's uh
I don't know if it's good to rest in it
you know what I mean it's better to be
working he's driving further
he's driving further
than resting content well the thing is
like it's really more like resting in it
does not require effort
so
resting in virtue pretty much means
intentionally making effort somewhere else so
so
and that's why I said what I said like
does that mean
like okay I'm not making the effort
towards the detailed understanding of
the dhamma but as that imply I'm not
making effort to endure things on the
mental level to endure doubt to endure
hindrances to not act out of them
because if he does you're wrong like
that that should not that cannot be
negotiated you need to do that whether
you're resting in virtue and simply a
mere Faith type
this is where the practice is sure you
don't have to be studying partly reading
the suit that's in pondering constantly
on the teaching and so on that someone's
approach but you do have to recognize that if
but you do have to recognize that if
you're resting on The Virtue uh what
else are you doing now okay I was asking
the virtues so does that mean I'm
tolerating unwholesome States
or am I enduring them rightly without
acting out without accepting the mental
value Delight in them
same with ill will same with distraction
because that's where the practice is
virtue is a basis for this practice but
if this practice is absent you can have
all the contentment you want in the
basis in the foundations when there is
no house on it you cannot be safe there
am I am I
am I uh
intentionally being content with the
virtue that I have and intentionally Now
using that as an excuse not to practice
further yeah exactly that you can become
that yeah I've done a certain amount of
work and I'm I must absorb the happiness
here yes I've got lots of work to do but
yeah it's I'm justified in not doing any
further work because I have I am
virtuous and I must that's yeah that's
exactly the thing because absorbing the
happiness from it and doing the work are
two separate things they're not mutually
exclusive being virtuous resting in it
finding contentment in it absorbing the
happiness of it it's effortless yeah
so do you use that to avoid the effort
that you would have been making on the
right level which means do you use that
contentment and so on as a justification
to not endure correctly the thoughts of
sensuality ill will and distraction or
are you doing the work there and you
just simply mean yeah I just don't want
to have to be constantly thinking about
themes from the sutas and so on in which
case fine you don't have to keep your
virtue and do things on the right level
discern the hindrances don't act out of
them don't try to get rid of them and find
don't try to get rid of them and find
contentment in The Virtue and account of
that fine wisdom will develop in a ways
it's like the right striving with
becoming virtuous
the peace that comes from it doesn't
mean that you stop striving no life
exactly comes peaceful yes striving
becomes effortless as well and if you
stop striving yeah
to rest in peace
means you're not you're not you know
well means you are now striving towards
something else you're striving towards
the opposite of what you should be
striving means you're justifying your your uh
means you're justifying your your uh
involvement with hindrances sensuality
distraction indolence doubt and so on
so it's interesting yeah I've heard
people say
is it is a time to rest and it is time
to strive to work but actually if you're
striving correctly that is your essence
that is your resting so and that's
exactly what it said for another hand
although he's Beyond training he remains
in that training mode
because that is the most peaceful
abiding not the same as one no no no no
no of course like you can only
understand that if you're an arhand
like training mode
requires effort
because your assumptions your Cravings your
your assumptions your Cravings your
being is still not extinguished and it's
pulling you the opposite way that's the
tension there it's not the tension is
not caused by the training and restraint
training and restraint revealed
attention of the flow of asavas and
sensuality and so on but obviously
unwise mind that's not developed
Associates the pain of the attention
with restraint and with the training
because that's that's the new criteria I
introduced in my life and look now I
suffer as a result of it engaging with
the training rightly it's painful only
because of the passions that are still
not distinguished and desires
so if you extinguish the desires
cravings the state of training is actually
the state of training is actually
peaceful abiding Here and Now
and that's why arahans remain in it
even if they're not exerting themselves
in the actual practice of Dharma
mentally they're entirely against that
grain of old passion and everything else
that's where they've been solidified in